# 传统老菜罗汉大虾
A traditional dish: Arhat Prawn
# 这是北京饭店的一道名菜
This is a famous dish in Beijing Hotel
# 也是谭家菜的一道老菜
Also an old dish from 'Tan Jia Cai' series
# 一呢我们要看这
First, look at this...
# 虾包很脏 把这个挑出来
The sand bag is very dirty. Remove it
# 都是沙子 便于这虾入味
Full of sand. For better flavor penetration,
# 要从脊背给它打开
Cut it from the back
# 要把虾线给它挑出来
and remove the intestine
# 这虾要从一节 二节 三节
The prawn.... segment one, two, three
# 从第三节把它切开
Cut it at the third segment
# 但是大爷
But, Da Ye
# 过去谭家菜用的是大明虾
In 'Tan Jia Cai', we should use 'Ming Xia' king prawns
# 您这虾不对
This prawn is wrong
# 现在市场上只能买到这种虾了
That's what I could buy in the market
# 这是个老菜
This is a traditional dish
# 就是一个菜是两吃
Cook one dish in two ways
# 虾头㸆 虾尾要瓤馅
Fry-braise the head, and fill the tail with stuffing
# 瓤出来以后像个罗汉的肚子
The tail looks like an Arhat's belly
# 圆圆乎乎
Round in shape
# 这个要把虾尾巴这个壳要去掉
The shell at the very end should also be removed
# 他有人开这虾是这么开的
Some people cut the prawn from here
# 这一开不要紧 就劈叉了
But that'll tear it apart
# 一定要从这边开
You must cut from this side
# 它这个用刀法不一样
Different way of cutting
# 从脊背开
Cut from the back
# 如果要是从这边开 就麻烦了
It's gonna be a trouble if you cut from here
# 就到这就劈叉了
It'll split from here
# 所以一定要从这边开
So you must cut from this side
# 这点一定要给它斩一下
Also, you should cut here
# 不斩一下它有筋
Otherwise there's a nerve cord remaining
# 一炸容易卷 你看圆圆乎乎
It'll roll up when frying. Look, they are round in shape
# 老饭骨就注重细节
In Lao Fan Gu, we do take care of every detail
# 其实你看他这刀口
Look at the cut
# 你看见没有
See that?
# 一斜 一打开 尖儿一碰
It was cut in an oblique angle. The ends meet together when opened
# 好多人他不明白
A lot of people do not know this
# 直接就齐头下去了
Hence they simply cut it in the right angle
# 一定要斜一点
Make sure it's oblique
# 斜一点它下来以后就是圆的
In this way, the prawn tail looks round after cutting
# 好了 咱们把它腌上 腌点底味
Okay. Let's marinate it for some base flavor
# 我搁点盐
Add some salt
# 虾别咸 大约在两克到三克盐
Don't make it too salty. Add about 2 to 3 grams of salt
# 白胡椒
White pepper
# 二伯给点酒 少来
Er Bai, add some wine. Just a little bit
# 葱姜 你看搁点葱姜 看着不起眼
Green onion and ginger. It may not seem important
# 但是你做完这菜以后啊
However, after cooking
# 您这菜就感觉到
You can feel
# 这虾里边有葱香的味儿
the aroma of green onion in the prawn
# 我们给它煎一会
Let's fry it for a while
# 我们还要制点虾馅
We also need to make some shrimp stuffing
# 这虾馅就是这样 一拍一剁就行
It's simple. Crush it and chop it
# 虾馅儿
Shrimp stuffing
# 肥膘肉也是给它切碎 剁成泥
Pork fat. Mince it
# 葱姜酒水
Green onion, ginger, Huangjiu rice wine, and water
# 盐 白胡椒 淀粉
Salt, white pepper, starch
# 现在这虾都是养殖虾
Now the shirmps are all cultivated
# 还要搁个鸡蛋 加点淀粉
So we need an egg and some starch
# 增加点虾的口感 还弹牙
To enhance the texture of shrimp, nice and chewy
# 朝一个方向搅动
Stir in one direction
# 蛋清 再搅
Egg white. Keep stirring
# 馅儿制好了 下面咱就开始操作了
That's the stuffing. Now next step
# 毛巾
Towel
# 这虾已经腌了半天了 腌好了
The shrimp has been marinated for a long time. It's done
# 拍点淀粉
'Pat' some starch
# 看咱排好队了吧
All lined up
# 为了让大小均匀 拿手挤丸子
To control the size, squeeze the stuffing balls
# 这丸子一挤就知道大小都一样的
The balls will share the same size if you use your hand
# 打好的虾馅
Shrimp stuffing, well stirred
# 虾馅里边有肥膘 有虾蓉
There are pork fat and mashed shrimp in it
# 看着啊 拿起来
Look. Pick it up
# 小刮板蘸点水 不蘸水不行
Dip the small spoon into water. Doesn't work without water
# 一抹 抹得圆圆乎乎的
Smooth it out. The shape is nice and round
# 抹这个时候 你看这底这儿
While doing this... Look at the bottom
# 还得往起兜一兜 圆了吧
Bring it up. That's round, right?
# 再来点芝麻
Grab some sesame
# 像不像罗汉那个肚脐眼
Does it look like an Arhat's belly button?
# 像吧 肚脐眼是黑的
Right? The belly botton is black
# 里边的黑东西
Something black inside
# 不许说那么明白啊
Don't explain it so clear!
# 小尾巴红的 炸出来黑的白的
After frying, the tail become red, the stuffing remains white, and the sesame is black
# 隋坡明白了吧
Do you understand, Sui Po?
# 什么叫罗汉大虾
What's Arhat Prawn
# 明白了 确实是真的第一次
Got it. This is indeed my first time
# 在您身边看您手把手的做这道菜
to see how you cook this dish by your side, step by step
# 过去这菜
This dish... In the past
# 一个菜用另外一个菜来进行点缀
We tend to decorate one dish with another
# 让人吃两个味道
To let people enjoy two flavors
# 过去我们宴席里边要有
In the past, in banquets
# 煎炒烹炸烧烩焖熘
We have dishes cooked by pan-frying, stir-frying, deep-frying, braising, boiling, brewing, and many other cooking techniques
# 各种烹调方法 各种口味
All ways of cooking, all flavors
# 都要在这宴席里边
In one banquet
# 让客人来体验
You need your guests to taste them all
# 你看圆乎乎胖嘟嘟
Look, round and chubby
# 特别像罗汉那个肚子 滴溜圆
It really looks like an Arhat's belly. Round
# 咱分两个步骤 先炸这个
Cook it in two steps. Fry this one first
# 油温大约五成热
Oil temperature is about 150 degrees Celsius
# 你看它一炸完了
After frying, it looks...
# 这颜色一上来粉扑扑的
The color is nicely pink
# 四成到五成下锅 给它沁熟
Soak-fry it at about 120-150 degrees Celsius
# 怎么看出这熟呢
How do you tell it's cooked?
# 浮起即熟 很好看啊
When it's floating. Looks nice
# 然后我们先控油
Drain the oil first
# 下锅 煎 油焖大虾
Fry it in the wok. Fry-braised prawns
# 大爷同时教两个菜
Da Ye is teaching two dishes together
# 一个是油焖 一个是罗汉
One is fry-braised prawns. The other is Arhat prawns
# 两边煎 煎的让它红了
Fry it on both sides until it turns red
# 要是大明虾 它现在就能出红油了
Red oil is coming out if these are king prawns
# 还得拿勺子拍一拍
Press it gently with the ladle
# 轻轻地拍拍头 这红油就出来了
Press the head gently. The oil will come out
# 这种虾没有油
There's no oil from this kind of prawns
# 葱姜丝搁一半（就够了）
Just a half of the shredded green onion and ginger
# 二伯给来点酒
Er Bai, some wine please
# 一定要煎透  不煎透虾容易是面的
Make sure you fry it thoroughly. Otherwise the prawn tastes pulpy
# 多点酒没事
It's fine to add more wine
# 兑点水
Some water
# 这油焖大虾
For the fry-braised prawns
# 我们第一个先搁什么 搁底味
What do we add first? Base flavor
# 先搁盐 白胡椒
Salt, and white pepper
# 白糖
Sugar
# 白糖得照着二十克
About 20 grams of sugar
# 一会还得要搁
We need more (sugar) later
# 因为这虾的颜色不是特别美
Because the color of this prawn is not very beautiful
# 不是那么红
Not so red
# 我们还要搁一点番茄酱
We need some tomato paste
# 这番茄酱不要多
but not too much
# 大约有十五克番茄酱
About 15 grams of tomato paste
# 出来这汁要红亮
To make the sauce red and shiny
# 你这糖要搁的恰到好处
The sugar should be right at the point
# 粘稠度 糖糊化之后的糖浆
Viscosity... The syrup from sugar caramelization
# 为什么叫焖 稍微盖一下
Why is it called fry-braised prawns? Close the lid for now (to let it boil)
# 我们这时候可以炸这个了
We can fry this now
# 烧鱼烧肉一定要盖锅
You must close the lid when braising meat or fish
# 为什么放好多水
Why adding so much water?
# 最后还有一个收汁的过程
We need to thicken the sauce later
# 看这汁很亮
Look. The sauce is very shiny
# 刚才尝了一下 还差点糖
I just tasted it. We need some more sugar
# 这糖的比例和盐要弄好了
The ratio between sugar and salt should be perfect
# 有时候你盐不够
Sometimes the salt may not be enough
# 太甜了也不行
But the dish shouldn't be too sweet as well
# 好了 装盘
Ok. Onto the plate
# 装盘的时候我们还得垫上点儿
Place the towel under the plate to tilt it
# 一边高一边低
Higher at one end and lower at the other
# 垫着点让汤汁不会浸到那头去
To prevent the sauce from flowing to the other side
# 十个 好了
Ten. Done
# 待会再收汁 咱先炸这个
Let's thicken the sauce later. Fry these first
# 这虾 二伯 这虾又复炸一遍
The prawns... Er Bai, fry the prawns again
# 我先把虾装上
Let me plate the prawn first
# 隋坡你看这个虾小尾巴 很精彩
Sui Po, look at the nice tail of the prawn
# 像不像罗汉那肚子啊
Does it look like arhat's belly?
# 它就过滤的好看了 没渣子了
Filter the sauce. There's gonna be no sediment
# 再熬一下 加点香油
Cook it for a bit longer. Add some sesame oil
# 加香油是来覆盖虾的腥味
Add sesame oil to cover the fishy smell of the prawn
# 让它熬稠了不能出油
Thicken it enough to prevent phase seperation
# 一出油就完蛋
Otherwise it's gonna be ruined
# 明亮 起泡了
Bright and bubbling
# 二伯给浇上
Er Bai, pour the sauce please
# 过了箩跟不过箩
Filter it or not
# 大爷 就是不一样
Da Ye, it makes a huge difference
# 谢谢二伯
Thank you, Er Bai
# 罗汉大虾 好了
Arhat prawns, ready to serve!
# 先吃虾头 先吃味
Taste the head first
# 我跟您说实话大爷
To be honest, Da Ye
# 我看过太多网上的菜了
I've seen so many dishes on the internet
# 看到了大爷这个罗汉大虾
When I see the Arhat prawns from Da Ye
# 五十年 弹指一挥间
Fifty years. Like in one moment
# 一晃我跟大爷都老去了
Suddenly Da Ye and I are both old
# 他的菜有根基 有魂 有传承
His dishes are full of souls and preserve the good traditions
# 希望我们真正做美食的人
I hope that the people who work in the culinary industry
# 都希望像大爷似的
I hope them to be like Da Ye
# 有一颗 不老的心
who keeps a heart that never becomes old
# 传承技艺
Pass on the cooking skills
# 谢谢二伯
Thank you, Er Bai
# 二伯说的让我有点伤感
Er Bai's words makes me emotional
# 确实是五十年了
Indeed it's been 50 years
# 刚才二伯说
Er Bai just said
# 会老去
That we will eventually become old
# 不是滋味
I'm speechless
# 反正在技术方面
In terms of cooking skills
# 师父就是一个宝藏
My master is a giant treasure
# 永远有我们徒弟
There's always something that we disciples
# 学不到的学不完的
can learn from him
# 今天过多的话 我也不说了
I don't want to say anything more today
# 学习的时候 我就是徒弟
I am your disciple when learning how to cook
# 那么生活当中
But in life
# 我就是儿子
I am your son
# 谢谢师父指导
Thank you, master, for teaching me
# 快起快起
Stand up, stand up
# 你让我激动了 快起快起
You make me emotional. Stand up now
# 看起来我们六十多了
We are over our 60's
# 退休以后做老饭骨这种
After retirement, we are operating this channel, Lao Fan Gu
# 传承中华美食的厨艺
to pass on the great skills in Chinese cooking
# 其实我们的责任是很大的
Actually our responsibility is quite huge
# 而且身边的这些好徒弟
Moreover, my awesome disciples
# 跟着我们
are following us
# 一路走过来 两年多了
It's been two years since we started
# 所以我们感觉
So we feel that
# 我们后边的路还很长
We still have a long way to go
# 虽然老了 但是我们心不老
Though we are old in age, our hearts never get old
# 中华美食博大精深
Chinese cooking is so great and broad
# 永远有我们学不完的东西
There is always something we have not seen and learnt